Leah: Let’s start by reviewing
what we have already discussed.
• How DRY code helps avoid repetition.
• How KISS principles help
to keep code maintainable.
• How coding conventions keep code readable.
• How SOLID principles help us
produce modular accessible code.
• How testing allows us to identify bugs.
• How debugging allows us
to rectify these mistakes.
Jack: So, what if a program crashes
when an error or bug occurs, how can
we prepare our code to deal with this?
We can use ‘robust programming principles’
to ensure that we can pre-empt and
deal with errors appropriately.
‘Robust coding and programming’
focus on handling invalid
inputs, actions, and errors.
It utilises specific code to
handle these by displaying accurate
and unambiguous error messages.
This way, it can deal with specific
errors in a way that prevents termination
of the program, or it can provide error
messages which provide clear information
to the user or programmer on what caused
the error so that they can debug it.
Leah: With robust programming
you must bear in mind 4 basic
things when writing your code.
Let’s start with Paranoia.
Assume that users of your code
aim to break it, and that it can
fail or run incorrectly by itself.
Therefore, you should write error
handling code accordingly and don’t trust
anything you haven’t generated yourself.
Next let’s look at Stupidity.
Write the error messages assuming that
the caller or user is stupid and unable
to read manual pages of documentation.
This way, the error messages should be
self-explanatory so other users of the
code [and yourself after time has passed!]
will be able to understand the problem.
Jack: Keep Dangerous
Implements away from users.
Anything that your routines expect
to remain consistent across calls are
known as ‘dangerous implements’ and
should be kept inaccessible to users.
They may [accidently or even deliberately]
if accessed, modify, and affect the
way the program runs in ways that
they had not intended [side effects].
This also makes the code more modular.
And finally, don’t think it can't happen.
Never assume that it is impossible that
certain bugs or errors can occur so write
the error handling code accordingly.
In the worst case scenario, your program
should at least contain code for flagging
an error message in seemingly impossible
cases, even if it cannot fix the issue.
If you anticipate
Leah: the problems which may occur, you
can use robust programming to secure your
code against the occurrence of errors,
and respond appropriately to either keep
the program running, or to provide the
user with the exact nature of the error.
This is done through employing
appropriate defensive programming
and exception handling which you will
learn more about in this session.
Jack: Let’s have a look
at this in more detail.